so
you you said recently
you were saying recently that you are
closer to jhana if you keep the precepts
unbroken there's that's
closer than what than just trying to
not keeping precepts and trying to get
the genre and meditation doing 24 hour
meditation yeah yeah 24 7 john
trying to do china and then
precepts are here and there a little bit
kind of
somewhere there but not sure
or not so not even important to you on
the level of
ghana importance you're saying i'll keep
the precepts
only until i feel something pleasure and
then i can
no i don't have to keep precepts anymore
that's conditional as you say
um
there's that description in
gradual training which says at the end
of uh
he keeps sila keeps precepts keeps
virtue unbroken unblemished
unbroken unblemished
and then he becomes when he's
accomplishing that he feels
the joy of being blameless unpolluted
and that's when you
and if you don't have that joy
some means something's going wrong
something you're not
you're not blameless yet yeah but that's
what you need to do
before you can really grow any further
yeah i mean i think the the whole like
contemporary views are just due to the
fact that most people don't really read
the suitors or hear that here's the sec
here the second account of them but you
read the suitors and it's just
whenever whenever there is john it's
it's a gradual training
that starts uh virtue moderation in
eating guarding the sense doors being
watched for
composing the mind literally the
composition of the mind through restraining behavior
of the mind through restraining behavior
controlling you know moderate and eating
being watchful guarding you're composing
um gathering the mind
because it's everywhere you don't see it
because it's everywhere
and then the the first genre itself the
mind has been sufficiently gathered
away from the unwholesome states away
from the world and then that internally
steadied as they would often describe and uh
as they would often describe and uh
pleasure and drawing bought from
seclusion as in
secluded from these things that used to
be scattered among
um so that's that is john
so you want jhana start virtue
moderate in eating goddess sends those
be watchful and you will have john that
is jhana
that's what it would have said uh even
if you know like steady your mind in
ghana don't erode the behavior of sensory
don't erode the behavior of sensory
strain guarding
got in the center and so on that brought
you the jhana because sometimes that
would happen
uh monks would get john and then get
overly confident and then stop
protecting the bases because of which
they have gianna
so literally you you built a 10 story
house you're on top floor and you suddenly
you're on top floor and you suddenly
start thinking that the foundations are
not important
and you start messing around with it and
you will lose all of it then you have to
rebuild it
so and that's where the wisdom part
comes in
when you recognize no this this remains
unchanged and this this will make majana
and this this will make majana
effortless and obtainable at will as the
suitors would say
because the whole structure remains even
if you're not necessarily abiding in
jhana at the time
the structure of jhana is there
and when there was a suit i don't
remember specifically i think maybe
but it would encourage these monks to be
virtuous so first he said practice your precepts
so first he said practice your precepts
and then said you will be cultivating
jhana for a finger snap at least by doing that
for a finger snap at least by doing that
so you realize oh the cultivation of
precepts and guarding of the sense of
those is the cultivation of jhana
because that that whole suit wasn't like
oh he was describing john and then said
having a moment of this jhana
is very beneficial for you know he was
describing keeping the precepts
and god in the sense those and then he
said moment of john is very beneficial
for you
the one who keeps the one who is who is
do following this instruction of gradual
training i say he's not devoid of jhana she's
i say he's not devoid of jhana she's
like oh
so you're not devoid of jhana by
keeping by by being virtuous celibate
god in the sense those you're not devoid
of john
even if you don't recognize it as jhana
because of your views or what jana is
you're actually doing things rightly in
terms of gradual training so you're not
devoid of jhana
the joy that comes from recognizing that
you are yeah not breaking peace well that is
are yeah not breaking peace well that is
already from samadhi yeah that's already
that's already
the gladness of the mind that has been
unified on account of that basis
there is a unified standard of certain
things you haven't done
you haven't broken the precepts that
begins to unify you in that sense
and in confidence that you will not do
it because you didn't take it
conditionally so
because yeah that is a big problem
people would take on the precepts
and by the way for janna you need eight
presets you won't get john on account of
five presets because you're not
withdrawn from sensuality
we can do a different talk on that but
that's also in the suit that's quite
often mentioned
um so if you are say
taking the presets celibate withdrawn
from centrality but you take them
conditionally so you don't see that only
this is the development that should be
protected for the rest of my life
and will elevate my mind and i will be
at will like i'll be able to to to be
abiding dwelling in genres it will
because the behavior is not eroded
most people will not see that way
because of the contemporary views and
notions of meditation
even if they take the strict presets
it's taken conditionally so
until i get a special experience of my
meditation and then all this becomes
relative but it's not you know your jhana is
but it's not you know your jhana is
there where you keep the precepts not
when you get the special experience on
account of something
but yeah having that unbroken precept
you can always reflect and always
experience the joy exactly and you can
direct your mind
in all sorts of not just necessarily
ghana you have the immaterial
contemplations that will result in
somalia of infinite space infinite
consciousness neither perception or
perception brahma riharda's in all sorts of
brahma riharda's in all sorts of
directions
because the foundation remains unchanged
withdrawal from the senses
guarding of the sense those taming of
the mind
complete stilling of of of urges and
cravings that you've been maintaining
through acting out of them
out of lust aversion and distraction
so that's what we said the only i don't
praise any meditation this is the
meditation i praised and then he
described jhana
if you understand jhana in this way we
are describing it you realize oh
the meditation on account of guarding
the sen's doors and being virtuously
restrained that's the meditation that the buddha
that's the meditation that the buddha
prays because that's what jhana is
you can use word ghana for basically a
unification of the gradual training
the first unification of the gradual
training is the first john
the second unification of the gradual
training is the second jhana
third and fourth and so on so
be virtuous because you will not be
devoid of jhana by being virtuous
not by watching your nostrils so i was
like okay
jhana practice vagina is the practice of
virtue taming the senses
composing the mind as i said so then
that's when those other suttas when
people ask
what what meditation master gautama
approves of he says this is the only
meditation i approve of not this
specific john experience that people
would think no
i approve of of china meditation
understood in the sense of
gradual training that leads you from
virtue up to the moderation
seeing the danger inside this world
sense god in the sense of seclusion from
unwholesome states
that's all that's done it's just that
the joy of renunciation from from start
oh yeah yeah yeah yeah the
relinquishment is just it's bound with
joy cleanliness yeah that second the second
cleanliness yeah that second the second
joy that
guarding the scent stores sense
faculties you experience the joy of being
you experience the joy of being
unpolluted
unpolluted yeah i'm burdened you're just
clean yeah you're very aware in the
first genre of everything
thinking and pondering is there contacts
there pastors there
second giant pastor's there will
distrust you oh it's just purified
experience on account of rounding up your bad
on account of rounding up your bad
behavior bad behavior means
not have necessarily heavily modeled
only means anything rooted in great
aversion distraction
is a behavior that spills you over that
destroys your composition
it's polluting yeah so rounding up not
acting out
rounding up rounding up rounding up you
build up a container
of of certain well energy for the lack
of better word
nothing mystical about it but you know
by refraining from this you remain more
composed here
um and you never abandon virtue and
guarding of the sense doors
in order to enter jannah quite the
opposite through confidence that comes
of your guarding of the sense doors and
virtue the joy arises in a kind of the
joy then oh i am i'm polluted here
then oh i am i'm polluted here
unwholesome states cannot get me and
that's the chitta viveka
like your mind now recognizes its own
seclusion from the unwholesome states
and then to draw your first jhana as we
said many times before is a joy of
relief like imagine you had a big debt hanging
like imagine you had a big debt hanging
over your head and now you paid it in
full and you had money left over imagine you
and you had money left over imagine you
were crossing a desert voting whether
your family is still alive or not you
come back
oh they're even better than when you
left them so it's a huge relief of
safety safety from what safety from your
own senses they've been dragging you
around like a rag doll basically ah left right
like a rag doll basically ah left right
eyes nose
assailed leg just jumping you were just
being tormented
and the only peace a mind that hasn't
been withdrawn from the senses knows is
the peace that gets that fleeting piece
through the
you know you're dragged through the
pleasant area as opposed to being
dragged through the pla either way you
have no safe
because you have no control over the
senses
so if you don't have the control of the
senses on the basis of virtue
your jhana your idea of jhana your view
of jannah your practice of jhana
is the extension of that seeking
pleasure through your senses because
that's the only form of peace that you
know and that's why you even with that view
and that's why you even with that view
basically that's where you even took
the whole virtue conditionally as i say
because you're actually still seeking the
you're actually still seeking the
pleasure of the same kind
so it's not ghana because it's not about centrality